<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The husband forc'd to be jealous, or, The good fortune of those women that have jealous husbands a translation by N. H.</title>
            <author>Villedieu, Madame de, d. 1683.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1668</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 111 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 85 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35785</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1188A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32399</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12669967</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12669967</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65475</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35785)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65475)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1525:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The husband forc'd to be jealous, or, The good fortune of those women that have jealous husbands a translation by N. H.</title>
                  <author>Villedieu, Madame de, d. 1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 5-157 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H. Herringman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1668.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Licensed, Sept. 8, 1668. Roger L'Estrange." -- opposite t.p.</note>
                  <note>"Prose translation of La jaloux par force et le bonheur des femmes qui ont des maris jaloux. Fribourg et Paris, P. Dontemps [i.e. Hollande, A la Shpeŕe] 1668" -- NUC pre-1956 imprints</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:65475:1"/>
            <p>Licenſed,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sept.</hi> 8, 1668.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Roger L'Eſtrange.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65475:1"/>
            <p>THE HUSBAND Forc'd to be JEALOUS, OR THE GOOD FORTUNE OF THOSE WOMEN THAT HAVE JEALOUS HUSBANDS.</p>
            <p>A Tranſlation by <hi>N. H.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Herringman,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Blew Anchor,</hi> in the Lower Walk of the <hi>New Exchange,</hi> 1668.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:65475:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:65475:2"/>
            <head>THE HUSBAND Forc'd to be Jealous: OR, <hi>The Good Fortune of thoſe Women that have Jealous Husbands.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>TImander</hi> and <hi>Clidimira</hi> having lov'd each other for ſome time, without any acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent hapning in their Amours, conſiderable enough to be rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65475:3"/>were at laſt Married, to the great contentment of them both. The Ceremonies of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract was performed in the houſe of <hi>Clidimira,</hi> where after a Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent Supper, which laſted till the night was very far ſpent, the Company diverted themſelves very agreeably in attending the morning; which no ſooner ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, but this Excellent Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were conducted to the Church, where they were Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with great Solemnity; which was no ſooner paſt, but the Bride and Bridegroom ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated themſelves, and every one returned to their own Houſes, as well to repoſe, as to prepare and adjuſt themſelves for the great Ball which was that night to be at
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:65475:3"/>one of the moſt Famous Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-houſes in that Town; it having been the antient cuſtom for the Richeſt Gentlemen of that place to make their Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding-Feaſts at thoſe kind of Houſes, when they Married their Children or Relations publickly.</p>
            <p>The afternoon of that ſame day, as <hi>Timander</hi> was dreſſing himſelf to go to that great Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, he received this note from a Woman he eſteemed very much, and in whom he abſolutely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fided.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Melaſia <hi>to</hi> Timander.</head>
                  <p>I deſire to ſee you as ſoon as you have received this Paper, and that you will believe that had I not
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65475:4"/>been perſwaded that your Life and Honour both were concern'd in what I am to tell you, I ſhould not trouble you with this requeſt upon a day wherein you cannot want Employment, and which you ought to dedicate wholly to Love.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Melaſia.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Timander</hi> had no ſooner read this note, but reſolved to go to <hi>Melaſia</hi>'s Houſe, imagining he might return home very quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and thought the excuſe he had was lawful enough to make him quit, without incivility, the beſt Company in the world; yet becauſe he had been formerly ſuſpected to have more then an eſteem for <hi>Melaſia,</hi> he was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing upon ſuch a day as this,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:65475:4"/>to give his Bride and the reſt of his Friends and Kindred any juſt cauſe of complaint againſt him; and therefore he ſtole out alone through a back door of his Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, which led to a private Street, where he took a Chair which carried him to <hi>Melaſia</hi>'s Houſe, without meeting any by the way which could diſcover him. He found her waiting for him in a low Parlour, where after ſome general diſcourſe, ſhe told him that ſhe was deſired by <hi>Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſander,</hi> a Neighbour of hers (who was not unacquainted with the particular Friendſhip ſhe had had a long time with himſelf) to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure for him the Honour of ſpeaking with <hi>Timander</hi> at her Houſe that afternoon; which at
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:65475:5"/>firſt ſhe had refuſed, telling him ſhe could not deſire that favour for him, without rendering her ſelf very ridiculous, in ſending for a man to diſcourſe of buſineſs upon his Wedding day; but when <hi>Therſander</hi> had at laſt aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red her, that the meeting which he deſired with <hi>Timander,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned the Life and Honour of them both, and that the deferring it a moment longer would be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal to them; She then reſolved upon giving him the trouble of that note, which he would ſoon pardon when he had received the reaſon of it from <hi>Therſander,</hi> who waited for him in her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; whither if he pleaſed to go, they might diſcourſe freely, without being heard or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:65475:5"/>
               <hi>Timander</hi> had ſome ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition of the occaſion for which <hi>Therſander</hi> had ſent for him; yet he was unwilling to diſcover thoſe thoughts which then poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt him, to <hi>Melaſia;</hi> but humbly thanking her for her charitable concern for him, he made haſt to the Chamber, where <hi>Therſander</hi> who had impatiently waited for him, no ſooner ſaw him appear, but he went toward him, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luting him with an Air which clearly diſcovered the trouble of his Soul, in a loud voice ſaid to him; <hi>Sir,</hi> I thought my ſelf ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to uſe this Artifice in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the ſatisfaction of you this day which I expect; for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I know you generous enough not to deny what I am
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:65475:6"/>come to demand, yet ſuch a day as this would have been excuſe juſt enough to have refuſed any chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge I could ſend you; and therefore I reſolved to ſpeak to you my ſelf. Know then (ſaid he) that I have long lov'd <hi>Clidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mira,</hi> and report ſpoke loud enough that I was not hated by her; yet when ſome Domeſtick Affairs of mine carried me into the Countrey, you cunningly made uſe of that time I was ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, to demand <hi>Clidimira</hi> of her Father, and obtained his conſent to Marry her; who being compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to it by her Father, yielded to your happineſs rather by obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience then by inclination. Theſe proceedings of yours have ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged me, that I am reſolv'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:65475:6"/>a revenge, and to deprive you of life, before you receive the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of ſeeing <hi>Clidimira</hi> in your Arm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; for ſhould you this night have that good fortune, I ſhould receive but an imperfect ſatisfaction in ſacrificing you to my juſt reſentments to morrow; and your death would be but too happy in the remembrance of having enjoyed the Fair <hi>Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimira:</hi> And therefore my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution is, not to quit you this day, till you have ſatisfied my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. And though I were ſure to dye in that Combat, replied <hi>Timander</hi> (coldly) I would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs defer it a few days longe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> becauſe to the pleaſing remembrance of having had the Fair <hi>Clidimira</hi> in my Arms, I
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:65475:7"/>ſhould adde the bleſſing of leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Heir of her blood, is well as mine, that ſhould one day re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge my Death. You have reaſon, ſaid <hi>Therſander,</hi> that Son of yours perhaps may kill me, but I think he will want ſtrength to do it; for the ſpight of ſeeing a Son of yours careſſed by <hi>Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimira,</hi> will deſtroy me before he can be old. enough to think of revenging his Fathers Death. Well, let it be ſo, replied <hi>Timan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> (with an Air much colder and diſdainful then before) yet I have a deſire to defer Fighting two or three days longer; for I know my Victory over you this day will be too cheap, beecauſe the thoughts that I am going pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to enjoy <hi>Clidimira,</hi> will
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:65475:7"/>certainly preſs me on to haſten your Death. And the vexation to loſe <hi>Clidimira,</hi> ſaid <hi>Therſander,</hi> will give me no leſs courage; and therefore let us go out preſently and try if Fortune will be your Friend. I am ſtill unreſolv'd, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered <hi>Timander,</hi> whether I ſhould ſatisfie you before I have ſeen <hi>Clidimira</hi> in my arms; yet now I think on't, ſaid he careleſly, I will fight with you to day, ſince you tell me you are in a condition to defend your ſelf ſo well; though I had rather ſtay till I had enjoy'd <hi>Clidimira,</hi> becauſe your anger then would be raiſed to ſuch a height, that it would adde to your courage, and ſo heighten the glory of my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt in overcoming a Rival,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:65475:8"/>whoſe juſt and violent deſpight will then render the moſt Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious of Men. Well, well, ſaid <hi>Therſander,</hi> I pretned not to my own defence, but compel thee to defend thy ſelf, and therefore let us go preſently. <hi>Timander</hi> replyed not to theſe words, but went out firſt, looking back up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Therſander</hi> with an Air that ſhewed little fear to all his threats. In going from <hi>Melaſia</hi>'s Houſe, they both deſired her to let none know they had met there: So taking their ſeveral Chairs without any Attendance, they cauſed themſelves to be ſet down in a little Village hard by that place, where they entered into a houſe, ſending away their Chairs; who being gone, theſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:65475:8"/>Rivals went into the Fields, where finding a place fit to their deſign, they drew their Swords, fighting a great while without advantage on either ſide; but as Fortune would have it, <hi>Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſander</hi> after he had fought as va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liantly as he had ſpoke audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, received a wound, of which he dyed a minute after. Let us leave him to dye in peace, and alſo <hi>Timander</hi> to ſhift for himſelf, whilſt we return to ſee what paſſes in the Town.</p>
            <p>The deſire which theſe two Rivals had made to <hi>Melaſia</hi> to conceal their having been at her houſe, and their furious looks in going from her, gave her ſome ſuſpition of their deſign; and having rack'd her imagination
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:65475:9"/>to find out the ground of their Quarrel, ſhe remembred that <hi>Therſander</hi> had been formerly in Love with <hi>Clidimira;</hi> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd her in the belief that they were gone to fight; and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her fault in being the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſhe reſolv'd for her own ſake to conceal their having been at her houſe that day. In the mean time all thoſe who were invited to the Feaſt, prepared to appear there in all their gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry; the houſe of <hi>Clidimira</hi> was all joy, every one was buſie in dreſſing the Bride, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was forgot that might ſet off her natural Charms; yet when ſhe was dreſt ſhe had the misfortune to attend very long the coming of the Bridgroom,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:65475:9"/>who was expected to conduct her to the Treating-houſe, where all the Company ſtaid for her: But <hi>Clidaris,</hi> Father to <hi>Clidimira,</hi> growing weary of ſtaying ſo long, and believing that his Son-in-Law came not thither becauſe his Lodging was ſo neer to that houſe where they were all to meet, waited upon his Daughter thither himſelf; where he was no ſooner entred but he ask'd the Company if the Bridegroom were come; they anſwer'd, No. He waited yet a great while longer, and then went himſelf to ſeek him at his Lodging, but was ſtrangely ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized to find that none there knew what was become of him: So this good Old Man return'd
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65475:10"/>back again to entertain the Company, which was already very great, and waited impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently the hour of Supper, but were forc'd to ſtay longer yet, ſtill hoping the Bridegroom would come at laſt; but every hour receiving a new diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to thoſe hopes, they began to fret, and then to grow very angry, and that anger at laſt gave way to a fear that ſome miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune had hapned to him, and to that fear was added the loſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of thoſe hopes that all day had ſo comforted them, and now made them deſperate: In fine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſight of thoſe delicious things before them, that would have comforted any other hearts increas'd their trouble inſtead o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:65475:10"/>ſatisfying them: The Fidlers were ſent away grumbling ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly, though very well paid, and were ſo impudent to curſe the Marriage, although they went from that Wedding much lighter and wiſer, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way much better, than ever they had gone from that Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-houſe in their lives: After the Fidlers were gone, the Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er himſelf came up ſtairs, and told the Company, that the meat would be ſpoil'd if it were not preſently ſerv'd in, and that he had ſpent already a buſhel of Coals in keeping it warm. In the mean time the poor Bride was all in Tears in the midſt of her Kindred and Friends that were comforting her; and as
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:65475:11"/>for the reſt who were not ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar, and others that Fortune had brought in to that place (for at thoſe kind of Treats there always comes more Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany then is invited) they knew not how to carry themſelves; there being many Perſons there, more concern'd for the loſs of the Supper, then the abſence of the Bridegroom: Moſt of the Children ſlept neer their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and thoſe that were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wak'd never left crying and bawling, asking indeſſantly when Supper would come: On the other ſide, the Pages and Foot-men entertain'd themſelves pleaſantly; ſome ſaying, they ſhould have the beſt part of the Feaſt if their Maſters and Ladies
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:65475:11"/>eat nothing; others cryed for fear their Maſters ſhould carry them away with them before they ſhould get a ſhare. At laſt it ſtroke One a Clock, and the Company taking every one a bit very haſtily, left almoſt all to the Laquays and Pages, without giving them any time to eat it: All the Gueſts waited on the Bride to her Lodging, and left the Treater and his Men aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd, having never yet ſeen ſuch a kind of Wedding as this at their houſe.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Clidimira</hi> was in her Chamber, they undreſs'd her, but not with the uſual Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of ſuch kind of days; there was no Poſſet nor Banquet at her going to Bed; no body
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:65475:12"/>look'd pleaſantly, nor was there any ſo merrily diſpos'd as to hide themſelves in the Bride-chamber; on the contrary, thoſe that were not ſad enough, yet endeavour'd to appear ſo; and there were ſome that could ſcarce forbear laughing to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the diſappointments of that day; and all in going home diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours'd upon the way of this adventure, ſeeking for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this carriage of <hi>Timan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> which they could not ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine came from himſelf, becauſe no body had forc'd him to this Marriage, to which he had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways expreſt a moſt violent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination. But whilſt <hi>Clidimira</hi> ſighs alone in her Bed, let us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to him that ſhould have
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:65475:12"/>poſſeſt the half of it, the poor <hi>Timander,</hi> whom we left ſo near an expiring Rival.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Timander</hi> no ſooner ſaw his Rival fall, but he left fighting with him; <hi>Therſander</hi> expreſs'd ſome deſires to ſpeak to him, but was not able to pronounce a word, and dyed a minute after he had receiv'd the fatal ſtroke.</p>
            <p>This Conquerour when he ſaw his Rival without life, thought of nothing elſe but go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſently to taſte the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures <hi>Hymen</hi> had prepar'd for him; but it growing very late, and having ſpent much time, and gone further then they imagin'd to find a place unfrequented e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to fight in, <hi>Timander</hi> in coming back by thoſe unknown
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:65475:13"/>ways, which inſtead of carrying him to the Town, led him fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from it, and to encreaſe his miſ-fortune, was ſet upon by Five Thieves; and although he was one of the moſt Valiant of his time, yet he was far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of thoſe Heroes who give death or flight to all thoſe that aſſault him, how numerous ſoever they be. All that <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander</hi> could do, was to fight like a Valiant Man, and not like one of thoſe Demy-Gods: He defended himſelf a great while, kill'd one Man, wounded ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but he alſo received a wound himſelf, that put him paſt fighting for that time, and ſo thoſe Robbers ſtript him and their own dead Companion,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:65475:13"/>leaving them both for dead, although <hi>Timander</hi> was not, though he was ſomething near it.</p>
            <p>When he came a little to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, Oh Heavens! ſaid he, with a Languiſhing voice, is it poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that I am that <hi>Timander,</hi> who this morning thought himſelf the happieſt of all Men, and who this afternoon have been ſo Fortunate to overcome a moſt terrible Rival? Look round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the World, and an adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture like mine can never be found. I was yeſterday at this hour in the midſt of Divertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Fortune ſeemed to prepare more and greater for me to day; in the mean time, by a Caprice which that blind God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſs alone is capable of, the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:65475:14"/>ſame hour ſhe promiſed me all thoſe Pleaſures, ſhe has thrown me naked in the dark into the middle of a Field, wounded and alone, and perhaps upon the point of expiring without help, or hope of receiving any, and without knowing what way to go to be delivered from this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs; and all this to happen in a time when Love and <hi>Hymen</hi> accompanyed with all kind of delights, waits to conduct me to Marriage-bed.</p>
            <p>Thus this miſerable Man, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of hearing his Epithalmium Song, lies curſing the Capritiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Fortune, and lamenting his unhappineſs, unheard, and unrelieved by any; his Enemies you may imagine haſted not to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:65475:14"/>his relief, they ſtayed not ſo late nor charitably in that Field; there paſſed by no generous un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known perſon to carry him to his Houſe, and dreſs his Wounds, and perſwade him at laſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the Hiſtory of his Life, which would not have taken up much time; yet notwithſtanding he received help in the midſt of theſe Diſaſters, and help which came from Heaven, although it was but a glimmering of the Moon, which lighted him to a Peaſants houſe, whither he made ſhift to crawl; and knocking at the door, he told thoſe people that ſpoke to him through the Key-hole, that he had been Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, and was Wounded; he added to his Tale promiſes of a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:65475:15"/>recompence, which was more powerful with them then all he had ſaid before, and made them open their doors to him, after they had peep'd through the window to diſcover what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of man he was, and whether he was wounded or not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Timander</hi> was no ſooner en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd that houſe, but he deſired them to fetch the neereſt Surge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; which the Farmers Son ran for with all the diligence imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, bringing with him a Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon that was by chance at that time in the houſe of a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man who lay ſick hard by that place. The Surgeon having ſearch'd his wound, found it not mortal, and gave him very good hopes of a ſpeedy recovery from
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:65475:15"/>that weakneſs, which only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from his loſs of ſo much blood.</p>
            <p>This unfortunate Hero after he was dreſs'd, ſlept all that night very well, and in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing writ a Letter to his Father-in-Law, to tell him the place where he was, conjuring him to come and bring <hi>Clidimira</hi> with him, deſiring him to let none know that he had heard of him till he had ſeen him. He ſent this Letter by his officious Hoſt, with a charge not to anſwer any queſtion whatſoever was made him. The Father of <hi>Clidimira</hi> receiv'd this Letter with great joy, and immediately carried it to his Daughter, who agreed with him to go privately to the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:65475:16"/>houſe where <hi>Timander</hi> lay; which was not very difficult, ſince it was at ſo neer a diſtance, they might eaſily go and come in a day.</p>
            <p>This good man, after he had conducted them into the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of his new Gueſt, went out, leaving them at liberty to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe freely. <hi>Timander</hi> deſir'd them to lay aſide their fears for him, his hurt being not at all dangerous; withal he told them, ſince they were perſons ſo neer and dear to him, he would not diſguiſe any thing from them of what hapned to him ſince he laſt ſaw them; and he hop'd the ſtrangeneſs of that ſad accident that had befaln him, would be his excuſe for leaving them ſo
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:65475:16"/>ſuddenly that day; and then he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated the whole ſtory of his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures, deſiring their counſel what to do next, and to tell him what the world ſaid of his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and whether people did not already ſuſpect ſomething of the truth of what had hapned to <hi>Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſander. Clidaris</hi> told him, that <hi>Therſanders</hi> Kindred knew no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it as yet, and only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd that the vexation to ſee his Miſtreſs married to another man, had made him quit the Town, and that they were not in much pain for his abſence ſince; and that <hi>Melaſia</hi> had confeſs'd nothing of what ſhe knew from whence they conjectur'd that ſhe would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways conceal it, for her own ſake, ſhe having been the cauſe of their fighting.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:65475:17"/>
            <p>After this and ſome other diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes concerning theſe matters, they all agreed to conceal this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident hapned to our Hero, but were much put to it to frame an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> excuſe for his going away upon ſuch a day, there being ſcarce an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Apology to be found for a man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that willingly abſents himſelf on his Wedding-day, unleſs he had been Married by force, which he was not; and therefore not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what reaſon to give, they trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled not themſelves much, but reſolved to let the World think what it pleaſed; and now let us ſee what they did.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clidaris</hi> and his Daughter ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſtayed ſome few hours long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in that place, took their jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney towards the Town, carrying
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:65475:17"/>with them a Letter written by the Hand of <hi>Timander,</hi> and ſealed with his Seal; and when the next day their houſe was full of thoſe Kindred and Friends that came to make their condoling Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, this Letter of <hi>Timander</hi>'s was brought in (by a Stranger hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to that purpoſe) <hi>Clidaris</hi> read the Letter ſoftly to himſelf, appearing extreamly ſurpriſed at the news it brought, which he pretended he could no longer conceal from the Company, but ſhewing the Letter, he deſired them to rejoyce with him at that good news it brought.</p>
            <p>But before I tell you the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the Letter, you muſt know that the Mother of <hi>Timan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> was yet living, and dwelt in
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:65475:18"/>a Countrey houſe ſome fifteen miles off that City, to which houſe her extream age had confin'd her ſo <hi>Timander</hi> cunningly writ word that although he more deſerved their pity then blame for his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been obliged to quit that perſon in the World which he loved beſt, and upon his Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding day; yet the juſt ſcor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that he knew the World would put upon that action, condemning it as a want of Love to his Dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Clidimira,</hi> had been an extream affliction to him, yet he hope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thoſe Cenſurers of him would condemn him no longer, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they read the truths of that Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which were theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>At his going from Church to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> own Lodging that day he was Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:65475:18"/>he found upon the Table in his Chamber a Letter, which informed him that his Mother was dying, and deſired to ſpeak with him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe dyed, of ſome buſineſs which ſhe would deliver to no other, and was of great conſequence to himſelf. And juſt as he was reading this Letter, he ſaw paſſing by his door a Friend of his, who was going in his Coach to the Countrey, and being to paſs by the door of that houſe where</hi> Timander<hi>'s Mother lay ſick, he took that opportunity of going along with him; believing the Note, which he haſtily wrote to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-in-law by a Laquay which he left behind, would excuſe that ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt leaving him for that time, and alſo his dear Wife, who though he was then ſnatcht violently from, yet
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:65475:19"/>now he deſires paſſionately to ſee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Artifice proſpered well, you may imagine, ſince it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the Parties concerned, who well enough knew the truth; as for thoſe that were not ſo, they did not dive ſo deep into the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſo the Company all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded this excuſe very reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and the whole fault was laid upon the Laquay that <hi>Timander</hi> ſent to carry this Letter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clidaris</hi> and his Daughter that had not ſo great a journey to make as was imagined, went the next day to the houſe where <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander</hi> lay, inſtead of going, as they pretended, to the houſe of his Mother: They ſtaid with him till he was perfectly recover'd, and during their abode in that
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:65475:19"/>houſe they heard that there was a man found dead in the Fields, whoſe face none knew, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore people ſuppoſed he had lain there a long time, and likewiſe believed he had been murther'd, becauſe they found his Sword in the Scabbard, and he was not robb'd; they carried him to the neareſt Church. All this perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded our Hero and his Company to believe this dead unknown perſon was the unhappy <hi>Therſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;</hi> for <hi>Timander</hi> confeſs'd he had left him in this poſture on purpoſe to diſguiſe the manner of his death.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as this unfortunate Bridegroom was heal'd of his wound, he returned to Town with this company, and was ſo
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:65475:20"/>happy to find none in that Town ſuſpected the leaſt of what had hapned; and ſince you may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve their Marriage is conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated, it is time to ſpeak a word or two of their perſons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clidimira</hi> was the only Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of her Father, her ſtature was low, and though ſhe was very a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable, yet none could call her a Beauty; ſhe had that I know not what charming Air which takes ſo extreamly, and is often ſeen in thoſe indifferent Women, but ſeldom or never is found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe great and perfect Beauties, which are ſo Celebrated in the World: her Wit reſembled her Beauty, and although it was not very great, yet it was full of thoſe flaſhes which made it ſo
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:65475:20"/>much admired in Converſation. To all theſe charms was added that much more attractive in the eyes of moſt Men, a great Eſtate; and that was the reaſon why <hi>Timander</hi> ſigh'd ſo paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately for <hi>Clidimira,</hi> his own be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very ſmall, though in revenge to that, he was one of the moſt accompliſhed Men of his time; and therefore <hi>Clidimira</hi> conſented ſo eaſily to Marry him. The hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of theſe two Perſons you ſhall ſhortly know.</p>
            <p>Six months after the Wedding of <hi>Timander</hi> and his <hi>Clidimira,</hi> he was viſited by one of his neareſt Kindred, that was his neighbour in the Countrey; this Perſon ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving not converſed with him ſince his Wedding, and being one of a
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:65475:21"/>pleaſant humour, and much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to Mirth, he asked <hi>Timan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> a hundred queſtions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his Marriage, and at laſt he deſired him to tell what kind of humour <hi>Clidimira</hi> was of. <hi>Timan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> inſtead of anſwering to his demand, told him, that ſince he knew him a great lover of Novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, he would ſhew him a new piece of Wit that was given him that morning, and taking a Paper out of his Pocket, gave it to this Friend, which he received with much joy, and read theſe words,</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Jealouſie of Women.</head>
               <p>Although it is the common opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that Men are more inclined to Jealouſie then Women, yet it
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:65475:21"/>is as true, that though Nature and Cuſtom have given the power on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Husband, yet thoſe Women that are once infected with this diſeaſe, diſturb that Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative of their Husbands, giving them often a trouble; which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders thoſe Wives ſo inſupporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that the ſtrongeſt Jealouſie of all mankind is nothing, if compared with the effects which the clamour of theſe Women produce, of which there are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numberable examples.</p>
               <p>When a Man is ſo unhappy to find a Miſtreſs of that humour, ſhe makes him ſuffer un-imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Torments; what buſineſs ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he has, and what lawful ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes ſoever he makes to her, yet he muſt be always in her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:65475:22"/>who will not be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to believe his. Affairs can be of more importance then to viſit her; and if at laſt ſhe is convinc'd that in waſting his time in her company, he alſo loſes his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; yet her humour is ſo Fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, that ſhe grows jealous of Fortune it ſelf, and fears leſt that Goddeſs ſhould favour him too much, and ſuſpects that her Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant will one day forſake her, to give himſelf up entirely to For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. If by chance ſhe meet him in Company, he muſt ſpeak to none but to her, and appear the moſt ill-bred, and uncivil Man in the World, only for a quiet life with her, who will break off with him twenty times in a month; proteſting ſhe will never more
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:65475:22"/>ſpeak to him, and yet will piece with him again at every viſit he makes her; and although ſhe ſcolds perpetually, breaks off, gives him an angry reception, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing always diſpleaſed, yet her Flames for him ſtill burn; which confirms me in the opinion that Jealouſie is a great ſign of Love, and that notwithſtanding all the troubles which the Jealouſie of Women give, yet no Womans Love is to be confided in ſo much, as that of her that is Jealous of her Servant.</p>
               <p>You ſee now what a jealous Woman does before ſhe is mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried; let us now diſcover if ſhe will be more reaſonable after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. Marrimony ſometimes cures the jealouſie of Men, who
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:65475:23"/>had ſome reaſon to fear ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſon more happy then they might ſnatch away that Treaſure which they aim'd at, and having it not in their poſſeſſion, had a juſt excuſe for their jealouſie of all thoſe Rivals which laid claim to it as well as themſelves; but Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are of another mind: They hold, that there is much more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for jealouſie after Marriage then before, becauſe the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of loſing a good we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy, is much greater then that of being depriv'd of what we only hope for; and therefore a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſays, that if before ſhe is married ſhe would have her Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant always to attend her, now that he is a Husband, ſhe will prove it his duty always to be
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:65475:23"/>with her, ſcarce ſuffering him to ſtir a minute from her, though it be to go about his domeſtick af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs; ſtill believing he gives more time to thoſe buſineſſes then is neceſſary, or elſe that he is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting himſelf with Company that pleaſes him better, when he is not with her. This hapning (from the odneſs of her humour) every day makes her inſupporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to her Husband, who is not able to endure her reproachful complaints, ſo often and violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repeated in his ears, with ſharp upbraids and continual murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, becauſe he courts her not now at the ſame rate he uſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe was his Wife, when he entertain'd hone but her ſelf in all Companies where they met;
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:65475:24"/>which now ſhe bawls to have him do ſtill, giving him a dreadful look if he fix his eyes (though by chance) upon any other Woman in the room. But ſhe appears for this the more ridiculous to all the World, who diſcovering her jealouſie, rallies her ſeverely, and makes her Fantaſtick inſolent hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour the diverſion of moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations, whilſt in the mean time ſhe is buſie in following her Husband into all places, and ſpares no coſt to find out all his intrigues, being aſſiſted with that excellent help, Jealouſie, which added to a Womans craft is very ingenious in making thoſe kind of diſcoveries; but this knowledge is ſo far from curing, that it exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates her diſeaſe to that abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:65475:24"/>height that none can expreſs but thoſe poor unfortunate hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands that ſo often ſuffer it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out complaint, who if they were ask'd can better deſcribe then I,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How far the Fury of a Jealous Wife can Tranſport her.</head>
               <p>And therefore I will not ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to ſay more to it then this; There is no ſight in the World ſo terrible, as a Woman in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; her Eyes, her Actions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all expreſs her a Fury, and if by chance ſhe hold her peace, her very looks are dreadful enough to make the boldeſt man to tremble.</p>
               <p>What is become then of that ſoftneſs ſo charming and natural to that Fair Sex? It is for ever
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:65475:25"/>baniſhed from the firſt minute this curſed Jealouſie ſiezes them, and to their great miſ-fortune; for if they could but once call it back again into their looks, their Husbands would quickly be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to them; but the Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie of theſe Women abhors the only remedy that can cure their Diſeaſe; for if ever any Wife would lay aſide that Fury which ſo Tranſports her, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain to her Husband with a good grace; if ſhe could overcome her paſſion ſo far as to ſigh only loud enough to be heard by none but himſelf, and inſtead of complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of him to all the World, ſtifle thoſe fiery ſighs which ſo juſtly are called the Children of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcreet rage, and makes her ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:65475:25"/>ſo ridiculous to the lookers on; if ſhe did only appear to him in that lovely ſoft charming Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, againſt which there is no Mans heart ſo hard as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt; then ſhe would get that vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory which ſhe loſes in thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miſtaken ways, which that ill Conducter, Jealouſie, leads her to her own ruine; and it is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that thoſe quarrels which ſo often ariſe between a Man and his Wife, would never begin, or elſe quickly end, if the Wife would but make her complaints with mildneſs: but the miſerable di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper of Women is ſuch, that when once they have begun to declaim loudly againſt their Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, they can never give over, whether they have cauſe or not;
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:65475:26"/>their Jealouſie ſo blinds them, they are capable of no Sentiments but what that Paſſion inſpires; and therefore the Senate of <hi>Marſeilles</hi> had reaſon to accept the petition of that Man that asked leave to kill himſelf, to be delivered from the Tempeſt of his Wife: How well that word Tempeſt expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the clamour of a Jealous Wife, and ſhews ſtill more and more that a Man can ſuffer no greater torment then that! And although it is confeſſed to be a great proof of Love, yet it were better let alone, for it does more hurt then good; yet a rational Man ought not to be diſpleaſed with the Jealouſie of his Wife when it is not exceſſive, as I have ſhewed before; the Jealouſie of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:65475:26"/>a Wife being commonly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a greater ſign of Love then that of a Husband, becauſe moſt part of Men are Jealous on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of their own Honour, but Women are Jealous only of their Husbands.</p>
               <p>But as there are very few of theſe kind of Women that I have deſcribed, I hope from the reſt of that Fair Sex (who are exempt from this dangerous Paſſion) the juſtice of their votes on my ſide, inſtead of their anger for what I have writ; which will be a great ſtrength to me in the War I ſhall always maintain againſt thoſe fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Ladies, whoſe humour at laſt receiving a change, there may be nothing found amongſt all Women but Perfections.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:65475:27"/>
               <p>After this Gentleman had read this Paper, which made him laugh in many places, he repeated theſe lines, which he found moſt to his taſte; The Jealouſie of Wives is commonly a greater ſign of Love then that of the Husband, becauſe that moſt Men are Jealous of their Honour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> When he had again read over that part, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, ſaid he to <hi>Timinder,</hi> that a little before you gave me this Piece, I asked you concerning the humour of your Wife, and you gave me no reply: You have no great reaſon to complain of that, ſaid <hi>Timander,</hi> for ſince you asked me that queſtion, I think I gave you that which pretty well reſolves your doubt, and leaves me nothing more to ſay; yet I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:65475:27"/>(continued he looking ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly upon him) that this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe ſurprizes you; but you muſt know that this piece, which fell by chance into my hands, and that which you have been reading, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes exactly the humour of my Wife, who I believe was the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py by which it was drawn. It is ſcarce ſix months ſince I Married her, and ſince that hour her Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie has almoſt made me deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate. He had ſaid more, but was interrupted by a perſon that came to him about ſome buſineſs, ſo his Kinſman went away, leaving them together, it is no matter whither he went; I have only undertaken the relation of the paſſages be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Timander</hi> and his Wife, therefore let us paſs on to ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:65475:28"/>more divertiſing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Timander</hi> having Married (as you have read) <hi>Clidimira</hi> more for Love to her Fortune, then her Perſon, therefore it is no wonder he was not very fond of his Wife, being none of thoſe Husbands that make Court to their Wives as much after their Marriage as before; yet he nevertheleſs paid her (like an honeſt Man) all the reſpect imaginable, was extreamly civil to her, and refuſed her no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhe asked, giving her liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to live where and how ſhe pleaſed, hoping that would teach her to allow him the ſame liberty of living according to his own Fancy; but he deceived himſelf, for his extream compliance gave <hi>Clidimira</hi> too much confidence,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:65475:28"/>and by little and little ſhe at laſt grew not to fear him at all; and when the Jealous humour took her, made loud complaints to all the world of her Husband, not apprehending his diſpleaſure in the leaſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Timander</hi> on the other ſide was very little concerned for this Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous humour of his Wife, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered not his cuſtom of going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad very often to divert him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and being a Man as gallant in his Humour, as handſome of his Perſon, he pretended Love in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places, and often complained of a Paſſion which ſeldom trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled him, making Court to all the Women he liked.</p>
               <p>Not long after he was Married, it was his Fortune to ſee a very
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:65475:29"/>handſome Woman called <hi>Almazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana,</hi> and was ſo happy to be pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced near her at a publick Feaſt: none are ignorant how a man well read in Gallantry behaves him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf at ſuch an Entertainment, where he had time enough to make his Wit ſparkle in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation before the Meat is brought in. <hi>Timander</hi> made good uſe of his time, and ſo charmed the Fair <hi>Almaziana</hi> and her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that he obtained their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to viſit them at their houſe; which he failed not to do very often, and with ſuch aſſidui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that he gained all the eſteem of the Mother, and tenderneſs of the Daughter, who knew not that he was Married, till an accident hapned, which I am going to tell
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:65475:29"/>you, which entangled this <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur</hi> not a little. The Mother of <hi>Almaziana</hi> came to him one day and ſaid, <hi>Sir,</hi> I have much acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment for your kindneſs to our Houſe, and Paſſion you have ſo long expreſſed to my Daughter; and therefore I do with all my heart give you my conſent to Marry her this day if you pleaſe. <hi>Timander</hi> was ſurprized at this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, not knowing what anſwer to make; for if he confeſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Married Man, he feared a certain baniſhment from the old Ladies houſe, whoſe Daughter he by a frequent converſation had began to like with a more then ordinary eſteem; and therefore without much pumping for an anſwer, he promiſed the old Lady
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:65475:30"/>to Marry her Daughter very ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, truſting to his Wit for a new pretence every day to put her off, till he had accompliſhed his deſign. The firſt it preſented him was this, he ſaid he had writ a Letter to a Kinſman of his who was gone to <hi>Italy,</hi> for his conſent, whoſe approbation concerned him very much, and till that Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was anſwered he could not Marry, but he hop'd it would not be long in coming, and that ſhe would give him leave to ſtay for it, which was much againſt his will.</p>
               <p>But ſee how Fortune thruſts it ſelf into Affairs, to which ſhe is not called! It hapned that <hi>Clidimira</hi> was informed of all theſe paſſages by a Merchant that
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:65475:30"/>went often to the houſe of <hi>Alma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ziana; Clidimira</hi> was in ſuch a rage at the hearing of this, that being unable to go to <hi>Almazia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi>'s houſe (by reaſon of ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſition of health) ſhe preſently writ a Letter to the Mother of that young Lady, ſtuffed with all the railing ſhe could invent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her Husband, ſparing not the old Lady her ſelf, who ſhe paſſionately reproached for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting her Daughter to be Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſo eaſily: So that the next vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit which <hi>Timander</hi> made to <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maziana,</hi> he was amazed at their cold reception of him; the old Lady asked him if he would find no other excuſe to defer his Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage with her Daughter, though his Friend in <hi>Italy</hi> ſhould give his
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:65475:31"/>conſent, or if he had not in that Town ſome other inclination be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides her Daughter. <hi>Almaziana</hi> ſeeing him non-pluſt, told her Mother that ſhe injured <hi>Timander</hi> in believing it was Love that hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered him from performing his promiſe to Marry her; for ſhe knew well enough, that the only perſon in the world who had power to oppoſe it, was one that he hated extreamly. <hi>Timander</hi> hearing her ſpeak ſo, preſently imagined they meant his Wife, and began to ſuſpect ſome body had told them he was Married; but ſtill believing they were not certainly informed of the truth, he denied all, till, they ſhewed him his Wives Letter, which he no ſooner read, but he turned thoſe
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:65475:31"/>denials into excuſes, and ſpoke a hundred pleaſant things upon the reſiſtleſs power of <hi>Almaziana</hi>'s Beauty: but yet for all that he was forbid the houſe.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as <hi>Timander</hi> received his diſmiſſion from thence, he went home, and far from quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his Wife for the Letter ſhe had writ, he patiently ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (without anſwering one word) all the reproachful Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage that the moſt violent anger and the cruelleſt jealouſie could put into a Womans mouth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clidimira</hi> finding by that ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of his, that her jealouſie was not without cauſe, ſet her ſelf to watch her Husband's actions ſo narrowly, that ſhe diſcovered the beſt part, and not only interrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:65475:32"/>all his divertiſements by her Spies, but followed him her ſelf into all Companies whither he went, and there ſhe made the laughing world a witneſs of her Follies: but when ſhe ſaw that ſignified nothing, and the greateſt part of the ſhame fell to her own ſhare, ſhe began to think that the only way to take him off from that way of Life, was to make him jealous; which ſhe reſolved to do without inujring her Vertue.</p>
               <p>Some time after ſhe had made this reſolve, ſhe went to viſit one of her Neighbours, where there was much Company, who having ſpoke to divers Subjects, they at laſt came to jealouſie. <hi>Clidimira</hi> diſputed to admiration againſt all thoſe that condemned that Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:65475:32"/>declaring that that Woman who had a jealous Husband, was perfectly happy. Every one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted her, and chiefly <hi>Argan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> who was one of the greateſt Gallants of that place, and had long time defended the ſide he had choſen againſt all the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>Clidimira;</hi> but at laſt he told her he yielded her the Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which he had ſo long diſputed with her, only to have the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour at laſt of being Conquered by ſo charming an Enemy. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that the diſcourſe changed to another Subject, in which <hi>Argan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> and <hi>Clidimira</hi> took no part, but entertained one another all the time that converſation laſted: he promiſed her to write a Piece for her of the advantage of all
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:65475:33"/>thoſe Women that have Jealous Husbands, and to make it more agreeable, he would ſet down the greateſt part of thoſe expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which ſhe had ſo wittily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in their favour; he alſo deſired her permiſſion to wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her at her own houſe, which ſhe granted him; he gave her a viſit two days after, ſhe no ſooner ſaw him, but ſhe challenged the performance of his promiſe, which he preſented her in theſe words;</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The good Fortune of Women that have Jealous Husbands; or the Apology of Jealouſie.</head>
               <p>All thoſe who are acquainted with the Paſſions of women, know very well that their Love is vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:65475:33"/>and their Hatred is exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, and that their deſires are to be loved at their own rate, will not think it ſtrange that they ſhould profeſs themſelves happy in having Jealous Husbands, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Jealouſie is a ſign of Love; and whatſoever is a ſign of Love, cannot certainly diſpleaſe thoſe Perſons that Love Paſſionately, and deſire to have that Love re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned: yet the moſt part of the World would perſwade, that Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie is leſs ſupportable then Hatred, and that it cannot but be extreamly troubleſome; and therefore I would here endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to diſcover all the advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and delights of it.</p>
               <p>The jealous have in all Ages been ſo unfortunate, that by a
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:65475:34"/>big and ſtrange injuſtice, they have been ſtill condemned by the greateſt part of the World, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out having yet been ſo happy to find any perſon that would un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake their defence; but on the contrary, moſt People agree in declaiming againſt them, they dare not ſhew a fear of loſing a perſon they Love, without expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing themſelves to be called trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome and ridiculous perſons; as if the fear of loſing what is beloved (which is in all others called a demonſtration of Love and Reaſon too) were only Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal in the jealous, whoſe fear of loſing what they Love, is cauſed by the Beauties, which they diſcover in that object, and whoſe excellencies makes them
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:65475:34"/>believe others may admire as well as they; and from that fear grows their Diſtemper, which is ſo much condemned by the greateſt part of People, who rather then they will leave any excuſe for theſe who are unfortunately touched with jealouſie, and to juſtifie their cenſures of the thoughts and actions of theſe miſerable perſons, are alſo unjuſt to Beauty it ſelf, which in all Ages has been ſo adored; and that Beauty to which ſo many Temples have been, they now ſeek to deprive of all its Ornaments, rather then they will want the ſatisfaction of condemning the jealous with more applauſe, not allowing them ſentiments ſo juſt and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, which have been in all Ages
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:65475:35"/>authorized by cuſtom and reaſon both, and are ſtill allowed to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, not only for all other things that are Beautiful, but alſo for all Beautiful Perſons.</p>
               <p>There are more Women then are believed, that make frequent complaints againſt thoſe Perſons who perſwade Husbands that they grow troubleſome to their Wives in thoſe viſible proofs of affection, of being too often ſeen in their company; and truly thoſe Women do not complain without cauſe; for the Husbands of theſe days are too much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to harken to thoſe perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Councellours, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn all publick expreſſions of hindneſs between Man and Wife, calling it jealouſie, and accuſing
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:65475:35"/>thoſe Husbands for diſtruſtful ill natur'd Men, and have at laſt made it the faſhion to cry down all fond Husbands as the moſt cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal amongſt Men. Theſe Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers do not only cry down this vertue ſo rarely found amongſt Men, but they make it paſs for a ridiculous humour, and no Man dare now adays be ſeen in his Wives company without expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing himſelf to the publick Ral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery; as if Men Married their Wives only to be rid of their company, and Women took Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands only to ſee them no more; for if a Man comes into his Wives Chamber before night, he is look'd upon as a troubleſome impertinent; and if he ſtay at home much, his Wife is pitied
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:65475:36"/>by all the Town as the miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt Woman in the world; let her do or ſay what ſhe will to contradict that report, nay, though ſhe is Paſſionately fond of her Husband, and expreſſes it in great raptures, no body believes her, all conclude it is her vertue alone that makes her ſpeak ſo.</p>
               <p>Strange injuſtice of the People of this Age! that will force or imagine that theſe perſons can live in any ſatisfaction when they are ſeparated from that half of themſelves, without whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany it is impoſſible for them to taſte any true delight or lawful ſatisfaction; and ſince I have told you that moſt women take delight in that part of jealouſie, which is called the moſt troubleſome,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:65475:36"/>I mean the company of their Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands; let us now ſee if they will take leſs ſatisfaction in thoſe other effects which this Paſſion produces.</p>
               <p>If to expreſs a fear of loſing what one Loves, if to believe that Beauty is to be Loved by all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that look upon it, and if the aſſiduity of Husbands to their Wives, are by theſe condemners of jealouſie accounted ſuch hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible crimes; judge then what opinion they have of the careful and ſuſpitious part of it which yet never Alarms an honeſt Wife but to make her vertue the more known, and affords her many pleaſures and advantages which I will ſhew you, after I have a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle examined what theſe Criticks upon Love require from a Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:65475:37"/>and a Lover in the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of their Paſſions.</p>
               <p>Although there is no Lover that ought not to fear that what he is not yet poſſeſſed of, may be carried from him by ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more happy man, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may juſtly be jealous of his misfortune; and although the jealouſie of a Lover is only this reaſonable fear, yet he is not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted (without drawing upon himſelf the hatred of his Miſtreſs) to make the leaſt complaints of her, or to diſcover any reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt his Rivals; but on the contrary, he muſt be civil to thoſe cruel Enemies of his that ſeek to deprive him of all his happineſs, nay, although he ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times too clearly diſcovers them
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:65475:37"/>very near the accompliſhment of their deſigns to ruine him. Is there any Laws in the World ſo ſevere as thoſe that are impoſed upon jealouſie? Muſt a Man give no teſtimonies of Love for fear of being called jealous, and be either inſenſible, or elſe endeavour to appear ſo? Muſt he Carreſs his Enemies, and find out a way to be Victorious without fighting, or doing any thing to ſhew the greatneſs of his Courage? He muſt beſiege a Heart without making uſe of Love to take it in, although no other Arms but thoſe of Love have force enough to cauſe that heart to yield; yes, he muſt do and ſuffer all this, or elſe be looked upon as a troubleſom Chagrin, ill-humoured Perſon;
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:65475:38"/>and ſo that heart which ought to be the reward of him who Loves moſt, is often given to him who appears the moſt inſenſible.</p>
               <p>But if theſe Teſtimonies of Love are ſo troubleſome from a Lover, and (as theſe blind Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks ſay) deſerve the hatred of his Miſtreſs; thoſe that a Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band gives are inſupportable, and ought to make him hated by his Wife; all that comes from him diſpleaſes (if we muſt believe them) they condemn his Love and all the proofs he gives of it; they blame his jealouſie and all its effects; what then ſhall we call Love, ſince they condemn it and all its effects, and will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it no longer? They would (without doubt) have it live in
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:65475:38"/>indifferency; for if a man ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs a paſſionate fondneſs of his Wife, or by all his actions aſſures her that ſhe is not indifferent to him, then preſently theſe people ſay, he is an enemy to his own re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and alſo to hers; they would have married men love coldly, or at leaſt without diſcovering any remainder of that Fire which they ſo much complain'd of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Marriage: They alſo find fault with all thoſe little cares which ſome Husbands take to ſhew their kindneſs, concluding that they are ſigns of Hatred, not of Love, and that all thoſe who make uſe of them, hate even in loving: but though they will have it that Love produces Hate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> muſt it needs follow that
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:65475:39"/>Hate produces Love? will the paſſions produce their contraries, to authorize the Caprices of theſe men, and to better their cauſe? or if they ſhould confeſs (with ſome, who though they are on their ſide, yet are leſs ſevere) that in the midſt of that Hatred, Love does diſcover it ſelf; yet how will they reconcile theſe two great paſſions? can two things ſo oppoſite conſiſt together? can a man hate what he loves, and loves without ceaſing? It is true, Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie and the little doubts that uſually accompany it, does give ſome trouble to the perſon belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; yet nevertheleſs that pain ſerves only to give a better reliſh to the following pleaſures, as the rigours of Winter ſets off the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:65475:39"/>Freſhneſs of the Spring: How pleaſant to Lovers are thoſe little quarrels which Jealouſie creates! how full of pleaſing rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and raviſhing joys are thoſe little skirmiſhes in the Wars of Love! how agreeable and charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is that reconcilement of thoſe Lovers who repent of their Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie! All true Lovers will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs and acknowledge that an Age of ſuffering the moſt cruel torments imaginable is abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forgot, and largely recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the charming extaſie of that ſweet moment of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation; the pleaſures it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords are ſo great, that if they could be expreſt, yet they would ſeem incredible; therefore I will only ſay, that if the joys which
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:65475:40"/>Loves War gives are ſo great, what can expreſs thoſe delights its Peace affords?</p>
               <p>But we ſee every day (ſay theſe Cenſurers of Jealouſie) that even amongſt theſe pleaſant quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels ariſing from the doubts of Lovers, there are ſome that laſt very long, and are very trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome both to the Lover and the perſon belov'd, and though this Jealouſie is at laſt cur'd with much ſatisfaction, yet it has been the cauſe of all the paſt vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and therefore it is ſaid with reaſon, that Jealouſie creates in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable evils, though ſhe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears but once, yet ſhe is the foundation of all thoſe diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that is one of the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:65475:40"/>of their proofs, for all thoſe things they impute to jealouſie, which they affirm nothing can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy; I will endeavour to prove the contrary, and deſcribe here the hatred of a Jealous Perſon, though I confeſs, if all things were judg'd by appearances, I ſhould accompliſh my deſign with much difficulty, there being ſome acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Jealous Men that ſeem very often to expreſs more hatred then Love to the Perſon beloved; yet it is a true ſaying when they complain moſt,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Love is in their Hearts, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though Hate be in their Mouths.</head>
               <p>Let us now examine what kind
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:65475:41"/>of Hate this is that reaches not the Heart, and whether or no it cauſes any pain to the Perſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved.</p>
               <p>Thoſe Women who have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times been the object of this kind of Hate, know very well that Love accompanies it, although he diſguiſes himſelf, taking Hatred for a vail; yet the covering not being large enough, ſome parts of him will be ſeen, he is eaſily known through all diſguiſes, and that of Hatred of this kind is too little and too thin to hide him; his rays pierce that Curtain ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily, ſo as it may be ſaid, Love ſtands behind that vail of Hate which Jealouſie cauſes, even as the Sun that ſhines behind thoſe envious Clouds that ſometimes interpoſe themſelves.</p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:65475:41"/>
               <p>So this beloved Perſon having been acquainted with the uſual effects of this jealouſie, is not at all Alarm'd by it, and remains with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fear, whilſt all the world is afraid for her, and pities her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; ſhe knows the advantage will be hers in the concluſion, and looks upon that hatred (ſo dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in the opinion of others) as a reſemblance of thoſe ſtorms, which when they are blown over, render the day more Fair, and the Calm that follows more delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; and this makes her rejoyce even in the midſt of the Tempeſt.</p>
               <p>But leſt ſome miſtake that Hatred I have endeavoured to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe (which cannot hide Love, and is only cauſed by the little doubts and fears of jealouſie) and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:65475:42"/>take it for that other kind which the world calls Hate, I think it not unneceſſary to ſpeak a word of it in this place. That which the world calls Hatred, is a Paſſion that cannot endure the object which created it, nor hear it men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned without Fury; it wiſhes nothing but ill, will not be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed, all its tranſports are vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, affects nothing but War and Treaſon, threatens perpetually, and takes a Pride in being Invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible. But that Hatred which I have told you of, does nothing reſembling to this; it Loves paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onately that which creates it, and never hears it nam'd without ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, wiſhing it nothing but good; and all its Tranſports are Raptures of Love; and it may
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:65475:42"/>juſtly be called a Hatred proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from Love, becauſe it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got by an exceſs of that Paſſion, and it loves and ſeeks after no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Peace; it deſires not to be eternal, and is born only that it may quickly dye, complains only to be appeaſed; and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as that other ſort of Hatred deſires to loſe the ſight of that object which created it, calling it inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable; this Hatred (which I mean) Courts it to her, and hates it only becauſe ſhe Loves it; in fine, it is nothing but an angry <hi>Cupid</hi> that deſires to be ſtrokt and kiſs'd, and though he take the name of hatred to diſguiſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, yet he is too well known to be long hid, and cannot leave loving, though he may deſire to hate.</p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:65475:43"/>
               <p>That which was ſpoken by a <hi>French</hi> Lady to her Lover, <hi>Ony ina haine pour toy va juſques à l'extréme, ſi l'on peut toutesfois hair ce que l'on aime,</hi> proves this truth; and let us ſee, that although ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred is ſometimes in the will, yet it is never in the power of a Lover.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee the difference that is between hatred and hatred, between the common hatred, and that which is cauſed in the heart of a Lover from the doubts of jealouſie, which may ſubſiſt with Love, which is impoſſible for the other kind of Hate, unleſs Love and perfect Hatred could be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs, to convince all thoſe who condemn jealouſie, and to let them ſee that it is not the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:65475:43"/>cauſe of ſo much ill as is imputed to it; let them aſſure themſelves, that there is nothing at all of what I have ſaid, if a Man find his ſupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions true, and that he is not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by appearances, and ſo comes to an expreſſible hatred of the perſon beloved.</p>
               <p>But what is the hatred of a Lover? What is the hatred of a Husband? has it not deceived all thoſe who confided in it? what do they not do to ſtifle it in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to deſtroy it abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? what do they not do to kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle that Fire which they put out ſo much againſt their will, and which they do deſire to re-kindle? one look mingled with ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, a Sigh, a Tear, one kind word of juſtification quickly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſes
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:65475:44"/>their hatred, though it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared implacable; which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms this ſaying,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſuſpicion cleared, re-kindles a ſtrong Love.</head>
               <p>Two Perſons are never more united, nor more inflamed, then after a quarrel of this nature, and ſhe that ſeems to have ſuffered moſt by the injuſtice ſhe met with, receives now a pleaſure much above her former pain, when ſhe ſees the Perſon beloved proſtrate at her Feet and asking her pardon, expreſſing his fears of having loſt her affection by his raſhneſs, in ſuſpecting her of infidelity. <hi>Careſsey</hi> importunes her, and appears aſhamed and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:65475:44"/>confounded at this Crime, and is more ſubmiſſive and paſſionate then ever.</p>
               <p>Beſides the pleaſure and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream joy which this re-inflamed Lover gives to the perſon belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, ſhe has this great advantage from it, of making good uſe of that time, in which a man can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny her nothing, but grants all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts a Woman can make, and which at another time are not ſo eaſily obtained: there is alſo this advantage to them both in ſuch a reconcilement, which can hardly be made without a knowledge of the virtue of his Wife, which when the Husbands Jealouſie has ſerved him to find out, it is a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhing diſcovery; and ſince there are many things unknown be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:65475:45"/>untryed, a Jealous Husband has this advantage of an indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent careleſs unſuſpicious one, he may anſwer for his Wives virtue, which the other cannot do, having never given himſelf the trouble to enquire whether ſhe were ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous or not.</p>
               <p>I have told you before, that ſome Women rejoyce more then is imagined in the company of their Husbands; but ſince I have not told you why they do ſo, and that theſe enemies of Jealouſie will not believe it, I will ſpeak a word or two concerning that.</p>
               <p>Since there is no pleaſure can equal that of being in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of thoſe we love, we muſt not wonder if Women that love their Husbands are fond of their
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:65475:45"/>company, complaining when they do not ſtay with them, and grow jealous of their abſence, believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves hated, ſuſpecting that their Husbands fly from them to pleaſe themſelves in places where they are not, forgetting that they are married; beſides, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother great vexation is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence which they believe their Husbands are at in other places, which is often but too true: and thus they weep, torment them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, make complaints, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the greateſt torments imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, without receiving any help from thoſe fruitleſs tears and doleful ſtories which they tell; for they are irremediable griefs, which nothing can cure unleſs it be the Jealouſie of their Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:65475:46"/>becauſe Jealous Husbands are always with their Wives, and waiting very aſſiduouſly upon them, giving them no cauſe of ſuſpicion or complaint, becauſe they are ſtill ſo happy to be with them they love; which ſhews that there are Women who deſire their Husbands ſhould be always with them.</p>
               <p>But if there are Women found of this humour, to wiſh their Husbands ſhould always ſtay at home with them, there are alſo Jealous Husbands in the world that will not permit their Wives often to go abroad; but ſince they have always been condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and their Wives look'd on as Priſoners and Unfortunate Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, let us ſee whether they are
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:65475:46"/>as unhappy as the World thinks them.</p>
               <p>Thoſe Husbands that ſee plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that their Wives pay to them without diſpute all the obedience they require, and are ſatisfied that this obedience proceeds from Love, return, carreſs them extreamly, redoubling their kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to them every moment: They receive other great advantages by their obedience, beſides that of letting the World ſee the great power their Husbands have over them, and the great intereſt they have in his heart, which is very rare, and is no little glory and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to thoſe Women, whoſe Husbands, though they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways with them, yet put no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint upon them at home; and
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:65475:47"/>when they go abroad, they take care to bring theſe Wives what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they fancy will pleaſe their humours, as New Faſhions, Fine Rarities, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And it is obſerved, there are no Women go better dreſt, and wear richer Cloths, then thoſe who have Jealous Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, which is very agreeable to that Sex, whoſe ambition for Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry is almoſt as powerful with them as that of Love. If all Women were of this humour of loving the company of their Husbands, if there were no Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſips in the World who love Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants, and to be Courted; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps I had well enough prov'd that this jealouſie is not ſo odious as it is believed: but ſince it is too well known, that it ſets all thoſe
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:65475:47"/>kind of Women upon the rack, it will without doubt be ſaid that I was not able to juſtifie jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie in all caſes; yet I wiſh it were true, that jealouſie would but give them all thoſe tormenting inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etudes and cruel pains it is accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of, perhaps it would oblige them to alter their courſe of life; but theſe Goſſips have ſo much wit and cunning invention, they turn all this to their own advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, as well before, as after they are Married; for whilſt they are un-married, the jealouſie of their Lovers gives them but little pain, becauſe they have too little pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er over them, and too much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective fear to thoſe perſons they adore, to torment them, by do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing againſt the humour
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:65475:48"/>of thoſe Coy Miſtreſſes, who know their own ſtrength well enough, and uſe it to their own advantage; but the jealouſie of their Husbands who they muſt fear and obey, is not the ſame, for that diſquiets and enſlaves them (at leaſt in their own opinion) yet they nevertheleſs draw theſe great advantages uſually from it.</p>
               <p>The Ambition of theſe Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men being to be Courted, and to have all ſort of Gallants, the jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie of their Husbands, inſtead of preventing, draws the greater number about them; ſome Men making Court to their Wives, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving the hatred they ought to have of their Tyrants (for ſo they call their Husbands) will make
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:65475:48"/>the Conqueſt very eaſie; others think, that a Woman that has power to create jealouſie muſt needs have ſomething extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, although ſhe is not hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome. Some fancy there is much pleaſure in deceiving a jealous Man, and the reſt adore her, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining it a great glory and a ſign of Wit to have a Miſtreſs that gives ſuch jealouſie, and is ſo much Courted by others, ſtriving to be in the faſhion; and thus the jealouſie of the Husbands gives theſe Women what they wiſh, an extraordinary crowd of Gallants. But ſome will anſwer, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it is true the jealouſie of the Husbands is the cauſe of all this Gallantry, yet theſe crowd of Lovers cannot defend her from
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:65475:49"/>the ill humour into which that jealouſie puts him, but on the contrary creates it; I grant that is moſt certain, yet nevertheleſs they uſually draw their greateſt advantages from that ill humour of their Husbands; for they being very cunning, they eaſily know how to appeaſe them at any time, though in the mean time they uſe all their endeavours to make the world believe they are ill us'd, by publiſhing this ill humour of their Husbands, and eſpecially to thoſe amongſt their Gallants who they cannot affect, and have a mind to baniſh; and alſo to grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thoſe whom they do Love beſt, by telling them how much they ſuffer for their ſakes, and to what dangers they are often ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:65475:49"/>by the extream paſſion they have for them, from the rage of that jealous Husband who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives it. This expreſſion of kindneſs from a beloved Politick Woman, gives theſe obliged Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers an unexpreſſible joy, who preſently believe themſelves much more beloved then they are; and in this Fools Paradiſe into which theſe goſſips have led them, blinded with the fancied dangers theſe poor Women are expoſed to for their Love, they think they can never be grateful enough, though they almoſt ruine their Fortunes with the vaſt Preſents they make them; which are recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by theſe Women with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, and many a jeer to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded Fool that preſents them:
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:65475:50"/>which confirms what I ſay, that the jealouſie of the Husband is not ſo prejudicial to thoſe kind of Wives as it is imagined, ſince it brings them in all that they care for; as in the firſt place, giving them a handſome occaſion to rid themſelves of thoſe Men they hate, without being in the leaſt ſuſpected by thoſe diſcarded Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants. Secondly, making them paſs for handſome by ſome, and beloved by moſt, and paſſionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adored, and richly preſented by the Men they like.</p>
               <p>This is all I can tell you at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the good fortune of thoſe Women that have jealous Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands; and though I have not ſpoke well enough upon ſuch a ſubject, yet I have in the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:65475:50"/>of my thoughts endeavoured to ſhew you Joys, Pleaſures, and other conſiderable advantages, even in the midſt of what-ever is moſt terrible in jealouſie; and I think I have forgot nothing to ſhew you that thoſe troubles which are cauſed by jealouſie, are many times the occaſion of great profits even to thoſe people that complain moſt; you have alſo read how it ſerves to make known the Vertue, Wit, Merit, and all the other good qualities a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is capable of, and how it is of equal advantage to the Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Un-married, to the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, and thoſe that are not ſo, and that without it Love would loſe his heat, there being no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but jealouſie capable of
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:65475:51"/>awakening, nouriſhing, and ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling him to find out new and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought of Pleaſures; all its effects being ſigns of Love, whoſe pains are rather to be deſired then fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. This being a great truth, we may juſtly call that Love imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and inſipid, which is not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with jealouſie, nay, it is a languiſhing, ſleepy, ſottiſh Love, which does not underſtand it ſelf, ſcarce knowing if he be alive or dead, and infine cannot ſubſiſt long in that eſtate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clidimira</hi> having read this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per with a joy that was remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able enough in her eyes, told <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantes</hi> (with a ſmile) that ſhe was confident he did not look upon her in the number of thoſe Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men he deſcribed at the concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:65475:51"/>of his diſcourſe, becauſe ſhe deſired to have her Husband jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and thought no Woman happy whoſe Husband was not ſo: he replyed, he never intended it to her, nor ſhould have a thought ſo unjuſt of her; and as for that concluſion, he only made it to ſhew that he had forgot nothing in that Paper to ſpeak his opinion of jealouſie, without intending to injure any perſon, ſince it was a truth ſo well known, that all the world were not of one humour, nor had inclinations alike.</p>
               <p>After that they talkt of divers other things, and although <hi>Clidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mira</hi> had a great deal of Wit, yet ſhe nevertheleſs reſembled thoſe Women that love to tell what they ought rather to conceal; for
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:65475:52"/>ſhe told <hi>Argantes</hi> all ſhe could imagine of her Husband and his humour, and the little affection ſhe believed he had for her. <hi>Argan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> being one of thoſe that only ſought his own Divertiſment, and eaſily flattered himſelf, drew from the diſcourſe of <hi>Clidimira</hi> many things that were advantagious to his deſign, and though ſhe had on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made it to help out the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation of that afternoon, yet he preſently believed ſhe did not hate him, and fancyed that if be would give himſelf a little trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to aſſault that Fort, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt would be very eaſie for him; but he deceived himſelf, for in the end the Vertue of <hi>Clidimira</hi> let him ſee the folly of his thoughts, and convinc'd him that
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:65475:52"/>thoſe Women that are many times the free'ſt in converſation, and are apt to ſpeak their minds freely, are the hardeſt for deſigns to work on, and the moſt Vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in Reality; which thoſe that ſeek to make advantages upon them, often find in concluſion, and is a truth which experience daily confirms.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Argantes</hi> was already thinking and contriving what to do to make uſe of this good Fortune, which he fancied he ſaw coming towards him, when <hi>Clidimira</hi> told him, ſhe was perſwaded that the only way to work this deſired change upon her Husband, was to make him jealous, which ſhe that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute had reſolved upon, and her thoughts had choſen him for the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:65475:53"/>fitteſt perſon in the world to help her in that deſign, if he would pleaſe to conſent; which he eaſily granted, thanking his kind For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune for that bleſſed motion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving now that that kind God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſs would undertake his happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; doing all things her ſelf for him, without ſuffering him to take any pains for his happineſs, ſince ſhe had inſpired <hi>Clidimira</hi> to prevent thoſe addreſſes which his lazy humour would have ſcrupled to make, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the greatneſs of his growing Paſſion; he offered to ſerve her in all things ſhe deſired, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of thoſe that fear nothing, and never trouble themſelves to examine what deſigns ſoever they take in hand, he conſidered not
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:65475:53"/>at all how <hi>Clidimira</hi>'s Husband would take it, thinking upon no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the accompliſhing what he had now promiſed, and wholly took up his thoughts; and thus they began to make the poor <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander</hi> jealous.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clidimira</hi> having gain'd all her Husbands Servants, was informed of all he did, and the next day hearing that he was gone abroad in the company of Ladies, was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to follow him, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the place where the Treat was to be given, ſhe ſent for <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantes</hi> and three or four Ladies of her acquaintance, who went to divert themſelves at the ſame houſe; and Fortune to give a good beginning to their deſign, carried them into a room ſo near
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:65475:54"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:65475:54"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:65475:55"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:65475:55"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:65475:56"/>to that which <hi>Timander</hi> and his company had taken, that both the Companies might eaſily hear and ſee each others actions. <hi>Clidimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> ſet her ſelf by <hi>Argantes,</hi> talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing always with him, and often whiſpering in his ear, but moſt when her Husband lookt that way. Thoſe that were with <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander</hi> pretended not to know it was his Wife, and were ſo diſcreet and obliging to him, ſeemed to take no notice of her carriage, though it afforded them wonder and divertiſement enough. <hi>Timan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> appeared with his ordinary gayety, unconcerned at all things, which he yet ſaw plain enough without taking of any notice; ſo that the mirth of both theſe Companies was not at all diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:65475:56"/>in appearance, although <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander</hi> and <hi>Clidimira</hi> were not without their troubles under this diſcreet diſguiſement of each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers thoughts. <hi>Timander</hi> at his return home that night, inſtead of appearing vext or diſcompoſed at what had paſſed that afternoon, appeared more gay and pleaſant then ordinary, in hopes that way to make his jealous Wife leave off her cuſtom of following him into all places; and knowing the deſign which brought her into the houſe where he was that afternoon, he ſeem'd to remember nothing of what had paſt that day before his face between her and <hi>Argantes:</hi> but on the contrary, <hi>Clidimira</hi> (far from imitating him) received him very coldly, and having much
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:65475:57"/>ado to contain herſelf, was every minute upon the point of break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out into a furious rage, her anger being raiſed to the height, when ſhe ſaw ſo little concern in <hi>Timanders</hi> carriage; and inſtead of the jealouſie ſhe hoped for, ſaw ſo much pleaſantneſs in his looks: but hoping for ſome effects from him, and the reſolution ſhe had taken to make him jealous, ſhe went on, Fortune being yet on her ſide.</p>
               <p>Some few days after that, knowing that <hi>Timander</hi> was gone into the Publick Walks, with the ſame Ladies that were in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany the day before, <hi>Clidimira</hi> followed him thither immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, having none with her but <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantes,</hi> and one of her waiting-Women;
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:65475:57"/>and ſeeing <hi>Timander</hi> at a good diſtance from her, ſhe made two or three turns about the Walks, and left her Woman with a charge not to follow her into the Walk, where ſhe ſaw her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band converſing with thoſe La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; ſhe paſt all alone with <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantes</hi> near the place where her Husband and thoſe Ladies were at that time very pleaſantly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained by a Lady of a very merry humour, which infinitely diverted the Company, who gave her leave to ſay what ſhe pleaſed without contradiction from any body, though ſhe rallied them all She ſeeing <hi>Argantes</hi> paſs by with <hi>Timanders</hi> Wife, ſhe told him ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pleaſantly, that ſhe never ſaw ſo handſome, well ſhap'd, and ſo
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:65475:58"/>Gallant a Man as that perſon was, that was alone walking with his Wife, and was the day before in her company at the Treating-houſe. <hi>Timander</hi> knowing well enough that this Lady and all the company had a mind to rally him, took no notice of it, and anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed merrily, that he had given his Wife a charge to make choice of no Gallant but one that was handſome, witty, and of a good Meen; and that now he was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly pleaſed to ſee ſhe had ſo much wit as to make ſo good a choice. <hi>Timander</hi> had a hundred pleaſant things upon that ſubject whilſt the Company ſtay'd there, reparting very wittily to the ralle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of that Lady that had ſo long play'd upon him and the reſt of
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:65475:58"/>the Company; but as ſoon as he returned home he began to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon all the paſſages of thoſe two days paſt between his Wife and <hi>Argantes</hi> before his face, and adding to this reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her having not complain'd of himſelf now as heretofore, though he had given her more cauſe to be jealous: all theſe things made him conclude that his Wife was really in Love with <hi>Argantes,</hi> and then he was convinc'd that (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he had reſolved never to be jealous) there was none could reſiſt that Paſſion, and any man might fall into it whether he would or no, and that how little ſoever a Husband might care for his Wife, yet the ſpight and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation of ſeeing himſelf ralli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:65475:59"/>by the world, inſpires often a more furious Jealouſie then that which proceeds from the fear of loſing what one loves, or ſeeing another have a ſhare in that which a man ought to poſſeſs alone.</p>
               <p>When this Forc'd Jealous man was come home, he could not hide his reſentments from his wife, who did not fail to give him a return ſharp enough upon the ſame ſubject, in his own Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, though with much more noiſe; but at laſt they reconcil'd themſelves with reciprocal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of giving no more cauſe of Jealouſie to each other. The Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſes and renewed Proteſtations of Love which uſually attend thoſe reconcilements between a Husband and his Wife, were not
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:65475:59"/>wanting at that time, and <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander</hi> from that hour ſtaid much oftner at home with her then he had ever yet done. Thus <hi>Clidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mira</hi>'s wiſhes were accompliſh'd, and ſhe did not at all repent (as yet) the having made her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band jealous, ſtill reſolving to reclaim him this way as often as he returned to his old courſes: but as it is no eaſie matter to change inclinations, or to alter an old habitual cuſtom of life, whatever reſolution any man may make, none is ſo much maſter of himſelf to do it; for the reformed <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander</hi> quickly returned to his old ways, not being able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain himſelf any longer; which <hi>Clidimira</hi> obſerving, made no more fruitleſs complaints as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:65475:60"/>but betook her ſelf to her new found-out way of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming him.</p>
               <p>She was in theſe thoughts when <hi>Timander</hi> came to tell her he had earneſt buſineſs into the Country for ſome few days; <hi>Clidimira</hi> at another time would not have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frained her tears and a thouſand prayers to divert him from going away, or to importune him for a ſpeedy return to her; but the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution ſhe had taken, hindered her ſorrows from appearing, and ſhe perſwaded her Husband in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of ſeeking to divert him from this journey.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Timander</hi> was ſcarce got out of Town, when <hi>Clidimira</hi> went to viſit one of her Kindred who lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved her exceedingly; ſhe was no
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:65475:60"/>ſooner entered that Houſe, but thoſe Tears which ſhe forc'd her ſelf to keep in (before her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band) burſt out very paſſionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, her Face expreſſing all the ſigns of a violent grief for the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of <hi>Timander,</hi> who ſhe fear'd was gone into the Countrey for no other end but to divert him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in ſome other Converſation which was more delightful to him then hers. Her Kinſwoman ſeeing her in that deplorable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, uſed all her art to comfort <hi>Clidimira,</hi> perſwading her at laſt to remain with her till her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band came home, which he did eight days after, his journey ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving only been for Divertiſment, as <hi>Clidimira</hi> imagined; when ſhe heard he was returned, ſhe made
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:65475:61"/>haſte home to meet him, carrying <hi>Argantes</hi> with her, in hopes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindle her Husbands jealouſie, which deſign took effect. <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander</hi> grew very angry, <hi>Clidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mira</hi> did ſo too, and though he had made this appointment of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the Countrey ſo private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that none knew of it, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to ride Poſt to diſguiſe his deſigns from <hi>Clidimira;</hi> yet ſhe ſpoke to him with that cunning, that he apprehended ſhe knew all the paſſages of that journey of Pleaſure, which put <hi>Timander</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly out of countenance, and obliged him to haſten that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute the peace with her, that is as eaſie to be concluded between a Man and his Wife, as it is difficult between great Princes.</p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:65475:61"/>
               <p>Although to go about the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a Husband jealous, is an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe that muſt be Fatal to all thoſe Women that undertake it; yet <hi>Clidimira</hi> proſpered ſo well hitherto in that attempt, that ſhe never gave her Husband any cauſe to be jealous of her, but when ſhe had moſt reaſon to complain of him: but as many things hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen un-fore-ſeen, let us now ſee whether the way which ſhe takes to change her Husbands humour, will always be ſo advantagious to her.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Timander</hi> after this laſt recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilement with his Wife, appeared very much reformed, as he did the time before, and ſtayed much at home with his Wife; but yet he was not altogether ſo kind to her,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:65475:62"/>nor did he careſs <hi>Clidimira</hi> with ſo great a Fondneſs as his former repentance expreſſed; ſo that ſhe now began to think him jealous in earneſt, believing he ſtaid at home only to watch her actions, which was to her a great ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction (though mingled with ſome fear) for her humour was ſuch, that ſhe choſe rather to be ill uſed by her Husband, then to ſee him go abroad, which yet he loved too well to forbear any longer, and growing weary of ſtaying at home, and acting againſt his Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, he reſolved to be his Wives Goaler no longer.</p>
               <p>As long as <hi>Timander</hi>'s humour of ſtaying at home continued, <hi>Clidimira</hi> had deſired <hi>Argantes</hi> not to viſit her more, or ſpeak to her
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:65475:62"/>in any place where he ſaw her; but as ſoon as ever her Husband re-took his old cuſtoms, ſhe writ to <hi>Argantes</hi> to viſit her as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, who failed not to obey her, and oftner then he was wont; and as he had his deſigns as well as <hi>Clidimira</hi> had hers, he avoided the ſight of <hi>Timander,</hi> which this ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Lady having obſerved, ſhe told him one day that ſhe had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of his actions, and therefore deſired him ſince he had undertaken to oblige her, that he would do it without inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and ground no fruitleſs hopes upon the miſ-underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that hapned ſometimes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween her Husband and her ſelf, or elſe never to ſee her more. <hi>Argantes</hi> knew very well that the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:65475:63"/>care he had lately taken to avoid her Husband, beſides thoſe other ſigns of Love he had too fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſſed, was the occaſion of her ſpeaking to him in that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and therefore he reſolved upon obeying her, rather than loſe his hopes, which he now commits to Fortune; and in thoſe viſits he made her, took no care as formerly to avoid the ſight of <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander,</hi> or expreſſing his grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing paſſion in thoſe ways which <hi>Clidimira</hi> did not approve; to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the regret that he might one day have for not having all things in his power to aſſiſt his good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, he reſolved to make <hi>Clidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mira</hi> ſome conſiderable Preſent, and having ſome looſe Diamonds in his Cabinet, he carried them to
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:65475:63"/>a Jeweller of his acquaintance, and deſired him to adde ſome of his own to thoſe, and make a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome pair of Bracelets: In the mean time he continued his fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent viſits to the Wife of <hi>Timan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> who acted a part at that time that aſtoniſhed all the world; for the oftner <hi>Argantes</hi> viſited his Wife, the leſs he ſeemed to take notice of it, uſed him very civilly, and diverted himſelf as at other times, ſpeaking to <hi>Clidimira</hi> with as much ſeeming indifferency, as if there never had been ſuch a perſon as <hi>Argantes</hi> in the world. This made <hi>Clidimira</hi> deſperate, becauſe ſhe knew not what to do next to make her Husband jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, being ignorant that he was now more jealous then ever, and
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:65475:64"/>carried himſelf ſo indifferently, only to find out what he had a deſire to know more clearly. <hi>Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimira</hi> in the mean time made <hi>Argantes</hi> viſit her at all hours, morning, night, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whiſpered to him even before her Husband as ſhe did before, who ſtill ſeem'd to take no notice of it at all; and if things had continued longer at this paſs, ſhe would have loudly quarrell'd her Husband for not falling out with her; which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs he reſolved to do, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king uſe of his patience only to find out the certainty of his Wife's Love to <hi>Argantes</hi> by more viſible ſigns, which he intended to puniſh ſeverely in his own time, which perhaps would have been a great while a coming; for if
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:65475:64"/>Fortune (that is ſometimes trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous and wicked) had not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him an opportunity of decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his reſentments, he might have waited long enough for a day of venting his Paſſion, <hi>Clidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mira</hi> being too vertuous to do any thing directly againſt her ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, though her indiſcretion was great in all thoſe juſt cauſes of Complaint ſhe gave her husband. Behold now how Fortune render<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her at laſt the moſt unhappy perſon alive, and although it may be ſaid, ſhe was partly the cauſe of it her ſelf hitherto, yet it is as true, that ſhe contributed nothing to the concluſion of her part in this Hiſtory, as you ſhall find in the following relation.</p>
               <p>As <hi>Timander</hi> was going out one
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:65475:65"/>day in one of his Chagrin hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, he was call'd in paſſing by a Jewellers houſe, by a perſon that had ſold him formerly many fine rarities, who told him he had fill'd his Shop with many Curioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties (ſince he had been there) which he knew would pleaſe him very much. <hi>Timander</hi> going in, and having viewed all the rare pieces of work in that place, he at laſt caſt his eye upon one of the Jewellers men that was at work upon a very fine pair of diamond bracelets; he asking whoſe they were, they told him they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoke by a Gentleman that dwelt hard by his houſe, whoſe name was <hi>Argantes; Timander</hi> having ask'd when they would be finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and they telling him the next
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:65475:65"/>day, he made no more queſtions, for he preſently ſuſpected they were for <hi>Clidimira,</hi> but went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, fancying that if he could find out that, he ſhould quickly diſcover all the whole Intrigue between <hi>Argantes</hi> and his Wife.</p>
               <p>The next day <hi>Argantes</hi> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Bracelets from the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eller, ſtudied ſome time what he was to do, and which way he ſhould preſent them where he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, and at laſt reſolved to write to <hi>Clidimira,</hi> and accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the declaration of his Love with ſo rich a Preſent; the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were very many that put him upon that courſe, he ſaw that <hi>Timander</hi> ſuffered him every day at his houſe, without expreſſing the leaſt ſigns of jealouſie, and
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:65475:66"/>that he went on ſtill in that care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs way; that <hi>Clidimira</hi> ſhewed more reſentment then ever againſt the indifferency of her Husband, even beginning to hate that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful man: beſides all theſe conſiderations, <hi>Argantes</hi> looked upon this preſent as conſiderable enough to open the eyes of any woman, and began to think that the ill treatment ſhe formerly gave to the declarations of his Love, was perhaps becauſe he made his addreſſes with empty hands. All theſe thoughts moved him to write to <hi>Clidimira,</hi> to tell her he loved her, and with that Letter to ſend his Preſent, hoping that although <hi>Clidimira</hi> ſhould abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely refuſe to hearken to his Love, yet the greatneſs of that
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:65475:66"/>Preſent would prevent his ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, not caring for any thing ſo he might declare his Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; nor feared he any thing more then her baniſhing him her houſe, hoping from Time, his Paſſion, and Wit, and thoſe other qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations he diſcovered in himſelf, to obtain her at laſt, as many young men of this Age fooliſhly perſwade themſelves into a belief that no Beauty how great ſoever can reſiſt their Charms, or defend themſelves from falling into thoſe ſnares which their wits lay to catch them: And thus <hi>Argantes</hi> built his hopes, holding it for a certain rule, that thoſe places which appear ſo well fortified, and hang a flag of defiance to the Beſiegers to frighten them with a
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:65475:67"/>belief of their great ſtrength and obſtinate reſiſtance, are often ſeen to render ſooner then is imagined. And having thus ſtrengthned his reſolutions, he preſently writ a Letter, which with the Bracelets he intended to carry himſelf, and putting them into his Pocket, he went that afternoon to viſit <hi>Clidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mira,</hi> in whoſe Chamber he had obſerved a day or two before, there ſtood a little Box, with the Key always in it; and having ſeen <hi>Clidimira</hi> lay in that Box ſome Bracelets of her own Hair, and which ſhe had wrought on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for her Divertiſement, <hi>Argan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> reſolved to ſteal out thoſe, in exchange of his Diamond Brace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets; which he eaſily could do, <hi>Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimira</hi> not uſing him with much
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:65475:67"/>Ceremony; for ſince he was by his frequent viſits ſo familiar in the houſe, ſhe often left him alone in her Chamber, whilſt ſhe went about her Domeſtick affairs: yet that afternoon he waited long for an opportunity of acting his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, but at laſt ſhe going as far as the ſtairs to ſpeak to one that brought her a meſſage, which was not very quickly delivered, <hi>Argantes</hi> had an opportunity of putting his Letter and Bracelets into the Box, and taking out the Bracelets of Hair, he crammed them haſtily into the firſt bit of Paper he found in his Pocket, and went away immediately after, as much ſatisfied as if he had found great Treaſure, though for his Diamonds he carried away no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:65475:68"/>but Hairs: which above all things ſhews the extravagancy of Lovers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Argantes</hi> that was the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented Man in the world in being thus rid of his Diamonds, was no ſooner gone out of <hi>Clidimira</hi>'s Chamber, then <hi>Timander</hi> (who had in deſign waited all this while in his Cloſet) entered the room, in hopes to diſcover ſomething of that which he as yet did but ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, and with an air mingled with ſcorn and anger, he asked <hi>Clidimira</hi> to ſhew him the Brace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets that <hi>Argantes</hi> had newly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven her; ſhe anſwered with much aſſurance, that ſhe did not know what he meant by that queſtion; for <hi>Argantes</hi> nor no other Man had never yet made her any Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents:
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:65475:68"/>in ſaying that, ſhe remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred that ſhe had laid thoſe Brace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets of Hair in that little Box which ſtood open, and fearing that if her Husband ſearching there ſhould come to ſee them, and fancy ſhe made them for ſome Gallant, though ſhe only wrought them to divert her ſelf, ſhe went to take them out, which it ſeems ſhe could not do without being perceived by <hi>Timander,</hi> whoſe Eyes were every where at that time, and who ſtepping towards his Wife, ſnatched the Paper from her as ſhe was conveying it into her Pocket; and unfolding it ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtily, he pulled out thoſe Brace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets of Diamonds, to the amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Clidimira,</hi> who knew or thought of nothing more then the
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:65475:69"/>ſeeing thoſe Bracelets of her Hair which ſhe had laid up in that place; but whilſt ſhe was ſtruck with wonder, <hi>Timander</hi> read theſe words;</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the Fair <hi>Clidimira.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Although I here preſent you with Bracelets of Diamonds in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of thoſe of Hair which I have taken away, yet think not Fair <hi>Clidimira,</hi> that I believe mine more conſiderable then theſe wrought by your fair hands, which I confeſs are unvaluable; and if I would here make uſe of thoſe Complements that are uſually made, even to thoſe Women that are infinitely below you in all things, I might here tell you, that
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:65475:69"/>theſe Diamonds have not ſo great a Luſtre as thoſe of your Eyes; but alas! how Fatal is that Luſtre of theirs to all that look upon them? and though the ſparkling light of theſe Diamonds cauſes them to be admired, yet the daz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Splendour of your fair Eyes commands Adoration from all thoſe that look upon them; and we may behold the one without trembling, yet none can look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on the other without fear; if the one ſhines and does not burn, yet the other ſhines and burns at once; if the one rejoyces the ſight without enflaming the Soul, yet the other never appears with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out piercing the very heart which it enflames, and cauſes a Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in all the Senſes: but ſince it
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:65475:70"/>is impoſſible for me to hinder this effect, who find as much difficulty in captivating your Heart, as it ſelf does find little in rendring mine your Slave, I have never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs the confidence to believe I may revenge my ſelf upon your fair Arms by giving them thoſe Letters, which if I am ſo happy to ſee them carry, I may well boaſt the good Fortune of enchaining what is moſt lovely in the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, and perhaps of ſoftning what is moſt cruel in all the world; but to make me thus Fortunate, you muſt ſhew for the future as much pity as you have hitherto expreſſed goodneſs to</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Argantes.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:65475:70"/>
               <p>I am very glad Madam, ſaid <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander</hi> to his Wife in a rallying tone, to find by this Letter how much goodneſs you have ſhewed to <hi>Argantes:</hi> It is long ſince I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to believe it, though I never was ſo certainly informed of it as now by his own hand; you are obliged to continue your favours to him, he is very acknowledging, as theſe Preſents he makes you ſufficiently teſtifie; and theſe Bracelets are ſo dazling and ſo rich, that there is no heart ſo hard which they would not perſwade to Love, eſpecially when they come to ſpeak for ſo Gallant a Man as <hi>Argantes.</hi> I know not, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed <hi>Clidimira,</hi> what reaſon you have to ſay theſe things to me, who am very ignorant from
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:65475:71"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:65475:71"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:65475:72"/>whence theſe Bracelets come, nor did I ever ſee the Letter you have read. I ſee very well, anſwered <hi>Timander,</hi> that you Love the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that writ it ſo extreamly, that you are never weary of it, and make theſe pretences of having never ſeen it, only to hear it read once more; which I will do to pleaſe you, becauſe I Love you better then perhaps you think I do; with that <hi>Timander</hi> read the Letter aloud, to which <hi>Clidimira</hi> hearkned very attentively, making very many proteſtations of her Innocence, telling her Husband that ſhe was confident that <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantes</hi> had put a trick upon her, conveying theſe things unto her Box ſome time or other when ſhe was gone out of her Chamber,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:65475:72"/>which was true enough; but truth ſignified nothing at that time, her miſ-fortune being above her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence, all ſhe ſaid to prove it was to no purpoſe, appearances being all againſt her, and ſo ſad was her condition, that <hi>Timan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> ſnatching the Paper out of her hand, which ſhe ſo innocently attempted to ſteal, only to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent a crime, not knowing there was ſo great a one committed in that place, and <hi>Argantes</hi> treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous exchange of the Bracelets, and all things what-ever that ſeemed moſt to juſtifie her, made againſt her; and <hi>Timander,</hi> though his amazement gave him time to harken a little to her juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yet at laſt quitted that cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with which he had begun, and
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:65475:73"/>grew extreamly paſſionate, telling his Wife ſhe could not deny that <hi>Argantes</hi> had thoſe Bracelets of Hair, for he had writ it there with his own Hand; and that he had given her thoſe of Diamonds was as clear, for he had ſnatched them himſelf from her, as ſhe was ſteal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them out of the Box to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey them from his knowledge; he told her, certainly no perſon was ever known to beſtow Brace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets of Hair without ſome inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to thoſe to whom they gave them; nor was there any body ever known to receive Preſents of ſuch a value as thoſe Diamond Bracelets were, without an inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of being acknowledging for ſuch a favour; nor was there any Man ſo fooliſh to be at the charge
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:65475:73"/>of making ſuch a Preſent, without propoſing to himſelf a certainty of accompliſhing his deſign. In fine, he repeated to <hi>Clidimira</hi> all the reaſons he had to be jealous, not omitting the leaſt of obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations he had made ſince the firſt day he ſaw her in the company of <hi>Argantes;</hi> but all his Paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate diſcourſes troubled not <hi>Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimira</hi> half ſo much as the trick <hi>Argantes</hi> had put upon her, who was more diſpleaſed at his bold declaration of Love, then at all the reproaches her Husbands jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie could make to her; and being at her Wits end between theſe two Men, and having a ſtrange deſire to quarrel <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantes,</hi> ſhe deſir'd her Husbands leave to write to him to come thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:65475:74"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:65475:74"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:65475:75"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:65475:75"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:65475:76"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="139" facs="tcp:65475:76"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="140" facs="tcp:65475:77"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="141" facs="tcp:65475:77"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:65475:78"/>that ſhe might juſtifie her ſelf by his Confeſſion; to which <hi>Timander</hi> having given conſent, ſhe preſently writ theſe words;</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>
                        <hi>To</hi> Argantes.</head>
                     <p>What buſineſs ſoever you have at this time, yet you muſt come to me immediately after you receive this Note.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Clidimira.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>As ſoon as ſhe had ended this Note, ſhe aſſured <hi>Timander</hi> that he ſhould be convinc'd of her innocence very ſuddenly, for ſhe knew <hi>Argantes</hi> would not have the impudence to affirm that ſhe
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:65475:78"/>had ever given him any Bracelets of her Hair, or received any of Diamonds from him. But this Husband thus forc'd to be jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, ſtudying a little while up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all theſe things, began to think that this was not the right way to know the truth of this matter, and being well acquainted with the greatneſs of <hi>Argantes</hi> Wit, he was certain that Lover would want no Politick excuſes to clear himſelf, and juſtifie his Miſtreſs; and this thought raiſing his anger at them both, carried him out immediately (from the preſence of <hi>Clidimira,</hi> whom now he bated to look upon) and going haſtily down the ſtairs, with reſolutions fatal to them both, he went out to find <hi>Argantes,</hi> who as (ill luck
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:65475:79"/>would have it) had newly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Note from <hi>Clidimira,</hi> and was going to know her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, when <hi>Timander</hi> met him in the Street very near the Gate of his Houſe, which ſtood in a remote corner of the Town, where very few people had oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to paſs; and therefore <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander</hi> had opportunity enough to act his deſign, who as ſoon as he ſaw <hi>Argantes,</hi> drew upon him. <hi>Arganies</hi> received him like a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant Man, but they had not time to Fight very long; for <hi>Clidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mira</hi> who had obſerved her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands threatning looks as he went from her, and had watched his actions at the Window, made ſome noiſe, and commanded the Servants to run after their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:65475:79"/>who with the aſſiſtance of the Neighbours that had heard the noiſe ſhe made, run to part them; but <hi>Argantes</hi> who had a very great care of the reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Clidimira,</hi> and knew that his pretended Amours to her had been long the diſcourſe of that Neighbour-hood, fled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way before any of them could know him; but in flying from them he gave <hi>Timander</hi> the lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to take up a Paper, which it ſeems he had dropt in taking out his Handkerchief, when <hi>Timander</hi> drew upon him ſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtily. The curioſity <hi>Timander</hi> had to read this Paper was ſo great, that he very haſtily diſmiſſed the Company that were buſie
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:65475:80"/>about him, and ſcarce affording the kind Neighbours a civil ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern of him, he deſired them to go home, telling them it was nothing; and ſo impatiently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to read what he had ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luckily found.</p>
               <p>Admire now what Mis-for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune will do when it once be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to perſecute any Perſon. <hi>Timander</hi> had no ſooner opened this Paper, then he ſaw it was his Wife's hand, and thoſe Brace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets of her Hair wrapt up in it with theſe words.</p>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:65475:80"/>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>
                        <hi>To</hi> Argantes.</head>
                     <p>I deſire impatiently to ſee you, to tell you that <hi>Timander</hi> is not Jealous, which I hope will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige you to make haſte; and if you have the ſame goodneſs for me you have ſo often expreſſed, it will bring you hither preſently, that we may conſult upon what we have to do.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Clidimira.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:65475:81"/>
               <p>Whilſt <hi>Timander</hi> is muſing upon this Letter, let us read the occaſion of it. <hi>Clidimira</hi> (as we have already ſeen) having by her cunning, and the jealouſie with which ſhe poſſeſt her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, forc'd this unconſtant Man often to change his courſe of life; yet he as quickly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laps'd again, and <hi>Clidimira</hi> as often tryed her enperiment of reclaiming him, by the jealouſie ſhe gave him of her love to <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantes,</hi> to whom ſhe had writ this Letter in one of thoſe Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy humours, deſiring the Counſels of <hi>Argantes,</hi> which had hitherto been ſo Fortunate to her in that deſign. <hi>Argantes</hi> had by chance kept this Letter
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:65475:81"/>in his Pocket, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> day he exchanged the Brace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, his haſte (for fear of being prevented or ſeen by thoſe he heard coming into <hi>Clidimira</hi>'s Chamber) made him wrap the Bracelets of Hair in the firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per he found about him, which (as ill fortune would have it) prov'd to be <hi>Clidimira</hi>'s Letter; who ſending for him ſo ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for her juſtification to <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander,</hi> he had no time either to look upon the Bracelets, or conſider what Paper they were wrapt in. <hi>Timander</hi> having read this Letter, appeared very calm, and without paſſion, told <hi>Clidimira</hi> he had now all that he deſired, and was ſo well ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:65475:82"/>as to her, that he wiſhed no more. The next day he ſent for her neareſt Kindred, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to them all that had paſſed, deſiring to reſign her into their Hands, he being reſolved to be troubled with her no longer. <hi>Clidimira</hi> ſeeing her ſelf in that ſtraight, diſcovered (in hopes to juſtifie her ſelf) all the Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems ſhe had to force her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band to be jealous, producing amongſt other things that Paper, Intituled, <hi>The good Fortune of Women that have Jealous Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands;</hi> which <hi>Argantes</hi> had writ at her deſire. But <hi>Timan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> made it quickly appear, that this Paper which ſhe brought for her juſtification, was a certain
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:65475:82"/>proof againſt her; and that <hi>Argantes</hi> pretending to oblige her, had like an expert Gallant contrived and continued, as much as he could poſſible, the diviſion between the Husband and the Wife; his deſign be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only to inſinuate himſelf by degrees into the favour of the Wife, though at firſt he ſeems to aim at nothing more then the reconciling her to her Husband, though he intends nothing leſs, which he plainly diſcovers in that Piece, called, <hi>The good Fortune of Women,</hi> &amp;c. Where he perſwades the Women to make their Husbands jealous, poſſeſſing them with thoſe great advantages and conſiderable
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:65475:83"/>Preſents thoſe Wives might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from that jealouſie, if they would make the right uſe of it: wherein he does not anſwer <hi>Clidimira</hi>'s intentions expreſſed in the deſire ſhe made to him for it; for inſtead of placing all thoſe great advantages in the reconcilement of a Husband to his Wife, he brings them in as received during the time of his jealouſie, and from other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons beſides the Husband.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Timander</hi> having deſcanted much upon this Paper which <hi>Clidimira</hi> brought to juſtifie her ſelf, to no more purpoſe then all the reſt ſhe could ſay at that time for her ſelf; he was reſolved to talk no more, but
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:65475:83"/>now to act in good earneſt what he had reſolved upon; and therefore he declared to the Company, that although he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways had eſteemed <hi>Clidimira</hi> too much to believe ſhe had an ill deſign at firſt, but from what had followed, he plainly ſaw that ſhe had not ſtrength e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to defend her ſelf from ſurprize, and in concluſion had ſuffered her ſelf to be won; of which truth theſe Proofs he had given them were ſo convincing to him, that nothing could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, and he deſired no more, being throughly ſatisfied of all. Her afflicted Kindred confeſſed ſhe was too guilty in appearance, and that they ſaw no excuſe for her; and ſo although <hi>Argantes</hi>
                  <pb n="154" facs="tcp:65475:84"/>loſt his deſign upon <hi>Clidimira</hi>'s Virtue, yet he ruin'd her Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation for ever; which let's us ſee, that all thoſe Women who too often receive the viſits from ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Perſons, expoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves not only to the like dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, but alſo to that of being betrayed into greater inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies; and if theſe croſs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents had not hapned, who knows whether <hi>Clidimira</hi>'s Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue would have been ſtrong enough to have held out to the laſt, although ſhe was one of the moſt Virtuous Women of her time; yet that Virtue not being guarded by Diſcretion, ſhe was at laſt ſo unhappy as to loſe her Husband, and to be treated like a Criminal by her Kindred,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:65475:84"/>who ought to have protected her, and yet were the firſt to condemne her. They never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs deſired <hi>Timander</hi> to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit her to live in his Houſe, without allowing her liberty to converſe with any, which he upon that condition conſented to; from that hour confining her, not in fear of her being Courted, for he was not of a jealous Nature, only lock'd her up ſafe from troubling his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſements; having done all this for no other end, but to deliver himſelf from the cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours of report caus'd by the jealouſie of his Wife, which heretofore troubled him in all places.</p>
               <p>After the patching up this
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:65475:85"/>Breach between <hi>Timander</hi> and his Wife, the Kindred of this innocent unfortunate Perſon ſought after <hi>Argantes</hi> to revenge the injury he had offered to their Family; <hi>Timander</hi> alſo made ſearch for him, but he was not to be found, his Father ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving conveyed him away far in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Countrey, to avoid theſe violent Purſuers, and great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Enemies that threatned him. <hi>Clidimira</hi> dyed with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row two or three years after, teaching all Wives (to her coſt) that they muſt never force their Husbands to be jealous; for Patience abuſed turns into Fury, and the gentleſt perſons are the moſt difficult to appeaſe when once provoked to the height;
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:65475:85"/>and though they are a great while ſilent to injuries, yet if once their anger break forth, it is moſt terrible and fatal to thoſe that provoke it, eſpecially if it is inflamed by the ſenſe of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</p>
               <p>And therefore who ever will be happy, let them not meddle with that dangerous Serpent Jealouſie, which though ſome have placed in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of remedies, yet it is worſe then any Diſeaſe, and a Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal danger to all thoſe that have made uſe of it, as experience has ſufficiently proved in all Ages, as well as in this Paper.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
